good afternoon this is Demitri laras
coming to you from camata Greece on
September 28th
2024 on September 13th the Biden
Administration issued a statement
alleging that RT Russia's state-owned
broadcaster is essentially an arm of
Russia's intelligence Services the
administration claimed that its
allegations were based in part on
information provided by RT employees but
it didn't name any of them nor did it
provide any objective credible evidence
to back up the allegation that did not
prevent other Western governments from
embracing the claims immediately for
example within hours of the US
government making the allegation
Canadian foreign minister Melanie joli
leveled the same allegation against RT
but she too provided zero evidence to
back up her claim what in fact does the
available evidence show about
allegations that Russia's government
covertly interferes in the politics of
Western States now here to unpack this
with me is John kiraku John is a former
analyst and case officer for the CIA he
was first he was the first US government
official to confirm that water boarding
was used to interrogate Al-Qaeda
prisoners which he described rightly as
torture in 2012 he became the only CIA
officer to be convicted for exposing the
cia's torture program he was sentenced
shamefully to 30 months in prison he's
now an author and a journalist and is a
founding member of the veteran
intelligence Professionals for sanity
and it's my great pleasure uh to welcome
him to reason to resist today thank you
for coming on the show John thanks for
the in invitation Demitri it's a
pleasure so John before we turn to the
uh us government's latest allegations
about Russian interference and RT I'd
like to talk to you about some claims
made before this most recent set of
allegations from the bid Administration
by Canada's parliament and specifically
the National Security and intelligence
Committee of the parliament and in June
of this year that committee released a
heavily redacted report on alleged
foreign interference in Canada as I
explained in a recent oped the report
was almost completely devoid of any real
evidence it largely relied upon
unsubstantiated claims made by the
Canadian Security intelligence service
or cisus notwithstanding repeated
findings by Canadian courts that cus
misrepresents the facts to judges in
this country and in a recent decision
the finding was that the failures to
tell the truth were systemic that's the
word that the court used so John one of
the passengers in that report that stood
out for me it concerned alleged Russian
interference in US elections even though
the report was supposed to be out Canada
and here's what the report claimed on
page 35 quote Canada's strategic
response to foreign interference and
Democratic processes and institutions
must be understood in the context that
brought the issue to the four so I just
want to pause there John and point out
that what the committee is telling us at
this part of its report is that they're
about to identify the thing that started
the whole controversy around alleged
Russian they go on and they say as noted
earlier Russia carried out an influence
campaign aimed at the United States in
the 2016 presidential election with the
goal of undermining public faith in the
US Democratic process and discrediting
the candidacy of Hillary Clinton it did
so by leveraging social media to provoke
and amplify political and social Discord
in the US this influence effort was
complemented by targeted cyber hacks and
the release of materials damaging to the
Clinton campaign the US intelligence
Community was was aware of Russian
efforts during the presidential campaign
but the central challenge for the US
government during those events was how
to inform the American public of
Russia's interference without appearing
to unduly influence the course of the
election Russia would go on to employ
similar hack and leak and disinformation
campaigns in the UK France and Germany
so John in a September 17th 2024 oped in
Consortium news you talked about the
allegation that Russia interfered in the
2016 US election
could you summarize for us your view
actually please be as detailed as you'd
like to be because I think so well what
what's your allegation th this isn't
just John talking right this is this is
the result of an exhaustive FBI uh
investigation into these allegations and
the FBI found in the Mueller report
which everybody is perfectly free to
read online for
free uh that there was no uh Russian
interference in the 2016 election now
the the government keeps repeating that
there was as well as in the 2020
election and now in the upcoming 2024
election but the government position is
take our word for it we can't tell you
the details because they're classified
but oh boy if you could see what we see
you would know well listen I've been
there I lived
there it's just a lie right so in the
2016 election they're talking about two
things one they're talking about Julian
Assange and the DNC uh email uh uh
tranch that ended up being published by
Wikileaks Bill Benny who was the
technical director at NSA the the fourth
ranking official in NSA and arguably one
of our country's leading technical
thinkers has said on the
record that the Russians were not
involved in the
DNC uh email hack and the reason he
knows that is that he's analyzed the
speed with which the documents were
uploaded and he said that it is
impossible to upload documents
remotely using that speed that the only
way those documents could have been
taken was
inperson downloaded put it on a thumb
drive okay with that in mind Ambassador
Craig Murray is the former British
ambassador to usbekistan he's a torture
whistleblower who was thrown out of the
the British Foreign Service because he
blew the whistle on torture in
usbekistan
he came to the United States in 2016 to
present me with an award that was
actually a cover trip he was actually in
the United States on behalf of WikiLeaks
to meet with the Whistleblower and to
take possession of the thumb drive which
he then flew back to Iceland and gave to
WikiLeaks so this notion that the KGB or
whatever the KGB calls itself today
remotely excuse me remotely hacked the
DNC stole emails from John podesta and
others to embarrass Hillary Clinton it's
just simply not true it's factually
incorrect that's number one before you
if you're are are you about to leave the
question of the hack because I want to
ask you a question about that oh sure
please go right ahead okay so my
understanding is that those emails first
of all I think we can say safely that
they weren't disinformation they
revealed valuable information no they
they they were primary source emails
correct they're authentic they really
are the yes and one of the things they
showed as I recall is that uh BAS
basically Hillary Clinton and the DNC
were cheating you know Bernie because
they were yeah yeah yeah that's that's
an important Point that's an important
Point somebody in the DNC who was
sympathetic to Sanders would have had a
motive to to the public so is correct is
all of that fair yeah okay sorry that is
one that is 100% accurate that's 100%
and it's far more believable that
somebody at the DNC said hey wait a
minute how can Bernie Sanders win 60% in
the Wyoming and West Virginia caucuses
and win zero
delegates right Hillary Clinton gets 40%
in both of those races and wins
literally every single delegate that's
more believable than some remote Russian
Hack that we don't fully understand
right right okay so please you were
gonna talk about the next part yeah I
was gonna make a make a second point the
second point was and this is straight
from the uh from the Mueller report the
Russians spent
$50,000 on on Facebook ads uh in the
runup to the 2016 election now when you
say Russians are you talking about the
government or somebody no and thank you
thank you for pointing that out no it's
well to to hear the US government say it
is it is an organization with ties to
the Kremlin what the heck does that mean
either it's a governmental organization
or it's not either it's an intelligence
organization or it's not right but you
know I've met Joe Biden twice does that
mean I have ties to the White House no
depends on your agenda I guess exactly
exactly it depends on your agenda right
so they spent $50,000 on Facebook ads
and then run up to the 2016 election
half of that money $25,000 was spent
after the election was over okay so it
played no role in anything right the
other
$25,000 was spent in states that were
either
completely red or completely
blue and what were these ads they were
mostly cat emojis right or
jokes so maybe the Russians were just
testing it to see can we do this how
hard is it can we establish these
relationships that will allow us to to
buy ads who knows to the question did
the Russians influence the 16 election
the answer is a resounding no they did
not the truth of the matter is that
Hillary Clinton was probably the only
Democrat in America who couldn't beat
Donald
[Laughter]
Trump it's hard to find anybody else
who's that bad I I have to admit so so
let can we talk about the 2020 election
because they're also you know you you
addressed this in your piece in the
Consortium in Consortium news which I
thought was quite interesting what you
had to say
there well think of it this way Bill
Clinton I'm sorry uh Joe Biden spent
over a billion dollars on his election
Donald Trump spent over a billion
dollars on his election you have Super
PAC spending more billions of dollars
and then Mark Zuckerberg testified
before uh Congress that the Russians
spent
$100,000 on Facebook ads and again you
know we we get to this point where you
say well what were the ads uh what what
were the accounts he said they were
Russians posing as Americans okay show
us oh can't show you it's classified but
if you could see what I see you would
know no when billions and billions of
dollars are being spent on Advertising
$100,000 worth of random ads not
targeted at any specific voters in
states that are already completely blue
or completely red are not going to
influence the election period you know
this is th this
is more historical than we give it
credit for being in that here in the
United States and I know that you've
studied this kind of thing as well we
always need an ism to Rally against you
know it was it was bolshevism at the
beginning of the 20th Century then it
was anarchism then it was socialism
right Eugene V Debs oh my God a
socialist is running for president then
it was communism or Nazism and then
communism and now it's this we we always
have to have some kind of enemy that we
can rally the American people against
and you have to ask why why don't we
just clean up our own Act
and improve our country I why does it
have to be negative I want to come back
to that primordial primordially
important question why are they doing
this but before we get there I want to
uh address the September 13th allegation
this most recent set of alleg what do
you understand uh the allegations of
against RT to be those that were
articulated by the state department on
September 13 and what is assessment of
those particular
allegations yeah so the the state
department is alleging that RT Russia to
formerly known as Russia today which is
the Russian International media Outlet
um is uh has
been subordinated to Russian
intelligence okay just factually it's
ridiculous listen if if I was going to
use the
media to either conduct intelligence
operations or to to influence a foreign
election or to collect intelligence
information I would use your media I
would put people at CNN and MSNBC and
fox not in my own media
organization they're not going to
collect anything there especially after
RT has been disbanded in the United
States disbanded in Canada disbanded in
the European Union the only places you
could watch it are are China India
Africa and Latin
America that's it but I'll I'll let you
in on a little
secret um I worked with a former CNN
Anchor Man Named
uh Rick
Sanchez and Rick got an odd call from a
contact of his at the state department
before this all happened a couple of
weeks before this all happened saying
hey man what are you doing what are you
doing working for the Russians why are
you doing that oh it's a bad
organization it's a propaganda
organization but one of the things that
this guy said and I think he probably
said it
accidentally was that RT is very very
popular in Africa and Latin America and
RT is presenting its side of the story
in the Ukraine war and it's beginning to
change public opinion there that's what
the administration is objecting to
they're losing International public
opinion and people are less likely to
support Ukraine now so I think this
whole nonsense about RT being an
intelligence organization it's just so
silly and it's backward in its logic I
think we should ignore it I think that
the truth is that RT has been successful
in changing some Minds um outside of
that US Canada Australia European Union
Nexus and that's a problem for the state
department right I think that's really
what it is now I I'll add another thing
too um I have a radio show at Sputnik
radio every day I have for the last
seven and a half
years when the Russians first approached
me and offered me a radio show I said
no I didn't really want to work for the
Russians and then they came back six
months later and they said listen we we
have this radio show and we'd like for
you to to be the anchor and I said well
you know the truth is I had always
wanted to get into radio so I saidif I
was to work for you guys I would want
the freedom to say anything I want and
to criticize anyone I want including
Vladimir Putin they said done I said
yeah are you willing to put that in in
the contract they said done and they did
and so in seven and a half years I have
never been asked to say something or to
not say something
and on the morning of the the uh Russian
invasion of Ukraine I opened my show by
saying I unreservedly condemn the
Russian invasion of Ukraine and I call
on Russian troops to withdraw
immediately another thing
is in Russia in all the Russian media
they they call the invasion of Ukraine
the special military operation I said
I'm not doing that I'm calling it The
Russian invasion of Ukraine and nobody
ever objected mhm
so somehow we're we're a propaganda
Outlet may may I offer one more anec by
all means every Thursday uh on my show I
devote 30 minutes to criminal justice
issues and I call it criminal Injustice
and I have two guests one is a a
journalist who covers criminal justice
issues and the other is H the founder of
a group called The Human Rights defense
center which publishes prison legal news
and criminal legal news
magazines so we talk about crooked cops
and crooked judges and crooked
prosecutors and terrible prison
conditions we all this
stuff one day The Washington Post
assigned a journalist to listen to the
show and they focused on the criminal
Injustice segment and they wrote in the
post the next day that John kiraku is
weakening our
democracy by talking about about these
issues I'm weakening our democracy by
saying oh a judge in Pennsylvania got
arrested for taking a bribe to put
children in prison a bribe from a
private prison company oh uh there was a
uh there was a prison in Mississippi
that is so full of rats that even in the
in the big container of milk they found
a dead rat and the state shut it down
I'm the one who's weakening our
democracy it's not the corrupt system
that we have right so this is what we're
dealing with we're dealing with this
irrational anti-russian uh opinion not
just in government but in the media here
and listen I have no love of the
Russians I really don't I don't like
them any more than I like anybody else I
don't dislike them any more than I
dislike anybody else it's a job but
they've been good to me they've never
ever ever asked me to propagandize
anybody and I'm free to say anything I
want
I must say for the record John I don't
know if you're aware of this but I
appear fairly regularly on RT myself I I
did not know that that's great I I'm off
I've often been on Cross talk uh
sometimes I come on live they always ask
me to talk about issues that matter to
me which are effectively foreign policy
and particularly Western foreign policy
they have never imposed any constraint
whatsoever on anything that I can say
and uh and and one thing I wanted to
talk to you about in particular like you
and I think might have had a similar
sort of trajectory in terms of our
interactions with the media when I was
um doing the practice of law much more
than journalism I was uh bringing large
class actions against major Canadian
corporations and these tended to attract
the attention of the financial press uh
you know salacious I mean they were
well-founded allegations of Securities
fraud and other forms of corporate
manipulation against well-known
corporate Executives in this country and
so I was regularly uh interviewed by the
corporate media and then in 2016 all of
that changed what happened then was I
began to publicly criticize Canadian and
American foreign policy and Canada
support for Israel and then I be so um
the reason why I and I i' I've tried to
explain this to people who ask me why I
go in RT the reason why you see me
nowadays much more on RT than you do in
the Canadian corporate Medias because RT
invites me on and they don't it's as
simple as that now I say the same thing
I I used to be on CNN correct go ahead
talk about that I used to be on CNN and
MSNBC with
regularity and they they dropped me
inexplicably now I go on Fox a lot which
is causes me no end of problems with my
with my most of my friends because I
consider myself to be very much a part
of the left but um but Fox is the only
organization that's willing to criticize
the
CIA and so of course I'm going to go on
and talk about intelligence issues
they're the only ones with the guts to
talk about them just like RT and they've
got a huge audience and if they're not
constraining what you can say why the
hell wouldn't you take the invitation it
makes no sense
exactly crazy exactly and you know I'm
I'm proud I'm proud to be able to speak
uh my mind and speak freely with the
Russians I was invited to lunch with the
Russian Ambassador a year ago uh he had
read something that I had written in
Consortium news and didn't even know
that I was an employee of Sputnik so he
invited me to lunch it was at the
Russian Embassy and I go over there
fantastic lunch and he wanted to talk
about ways in which he could try to
improve relations with the United States
even in a time of war and I said
actually I have three thoughts um number
one is
counterterrorism right we should be in
lock step on terrorism issues number two
is counter proliferation none of us want
Rogue organizations to uh end up with
nuclear or file material and number
three is um counternarcotics I said I'll
tell you the truth when I was the chief
investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee I went to
Afghanistan to do a study on heroin
poppy production and Afghanistan at the
time was producing 93%
of the world's heroin
Poppy and when I came back I wrote all
this up I interviewed people from DEA I
interviewed academics I interviewed
journalists and Afghan
veterans and the report ended up going
nowhere
why because the policy is that we that
all that heroin goes to Iran and Russia
and we want them to be addicted to
heroin it makes their societies weaker
so no we're not going to do anything to
stop the heroin
trade but you rais a you raise a vitally
important point which is that there are
common interest between the American
people and the Russian people and I I'd
like to highlight two others that are of
the utmost urgency both the American
people and the Russian people and all
human beings and forms of life on this
planet have an interest in avoiding
nuclear war absolutely right so I mean
there couldn't be a more important
common interest that we all share as
human beings and another thing is if
there's a state of belligerence between
our countries this is going to
inevitably provoke an arms race and
we're going to see more and more money
going into uh in both countries and
we're seeing this happen in both
countries the military budgets are
increasing rapidly and money is being
diverted away from socially beneficial
uses which is bad for Russians and
Americans and Canadians yes yes so we
need this mindset that we have no common
interests that's BS and it is BS and you
know just yesterday uh a senior member
of the Senate a Republican senator uh
gave a statement to The Washington Post
saying that he's going to propose in the
next federal budget that um that the
Pentagon receive
5% of
GDP as its budget now we're currently at
3.2% and we're bankrupting ourselves but
now they want to spend 5% of GDP the
Pentagon couldn't even spend that kind
of money
but this is this is exactly to your
point we're very much in an arms race
and not only are we in an arms race
we're the ones promoting the arms race
there there's also another presumption
John which I like your thoughts upon
which which I think is underlying this
whole hysteria I call it the foreign
interference scam and all sometimes I
refer to it as the foreign interference
hysteria and that presumption is that
the Russian government never tells the
truth so if you are aligned with the
Russian government on some
so for example that there was a coup in
Ukraine in
2014 right we have a recording Victoria
nuland telling the US ambassador to
Ukraine Jeffrey Patt who the next prime
minister of Ukraine is going to be and
he became the next prime minister but
hey it's a lie that's where we've been
told but in fact you know sometimes the
Russian government tells the truth does
it sometimes lie sure as to all
governments no government that is pure
as the driven snow but it's just
nonsense that we we are necessarily
repeating propaganda if our position
aligns with the Russian government on
some particular issue so wouldn't it be
smarter if we actually invited our
citizens to engage in debate and try to
discern the difference between truth and
falsehood when it's when issues when
when we hear positions from the Russian
government from our own government
rather than tell us that we can never
align with the Russian government on any
issue I mean oh I had get that off my
chest you know John yeah I think you I
think you raised a very important Point
here you know I I kind of humble brag
sometimes that I don't just watch One
News Network I watch literally all of
them so I'll flip from CNN to MSNBC to
Fox to Al jazer to BBC to RT and
sometimes I'll even go to The Crazy Ones
like One America Network and Newsmax
just to see what everybody's saying but
more importantly to see what everybody's
focusing on right because it it's like
living on two different planets
sometimes to to watch them Side by
side I can't do that now um RT is
gone and BBC just parrots what's in the
US press and uh the local cable
subscriber has dropped Al jazer so now
I'm able to watch only what the American
government tells me I can watch it's
what they want me to watch I get only
their message it's very difficult to get
uh to get outside opinions but you're
absolutely right listen every government
lies but a lot of the time I would
venture to say most of the time what
we're seeing on these other networks is
the
truth and we should be the ones to
decide that 100 percent after all if we
UST people to vote right how can we not
entrust them to discern truth from
falsehood when they uh oh you're you're
so right yes so the last thing I want to
ask you about John is this uh the why
the why of all of this why why are they
investing so much time in energy uh when
there's so many pressing problems in our
domestic
context in getting people all worked up
about Russian interference and now of
course they're talking about Chinese
interference and once in a while they
lob a grenade at Iran they say Iran's
interfering this has become uh quite
possibly one of the most important
themes in the corporate media today and
in government political discourse what
what is the motivation for all you know
D Tre I think that we're in the midst of
what what historians will come to call a
watershed when I was in college we spent
a great deal of time learning about what
they called The Watershed election of
1932 where the Democratic party and the
Republican party switch sides on the
issues the Democrats had always been the
conservatives the Republicans had always
been the Liberals right if you were
Republican you were anti-slavery going
back to the 1860s you were PR labor for
example um it was the Democrats that
were the the conservatives especially
social conservatives and that all
changed with the election in 1932 of
Franklin Roosevelt as president okay I
think we're in the midst of seeing it
flip back again when I was at the CIA we
used to complain
vifer during the George W Bush
Administration that we had never seen an
Administration especially a state
department that worked so hard to not
talk to people well that's what we're
seeing now like why are we not engaged
in talks with the Russians and the
Chinese and the Iranians and Hamas and
Hezbollah and a whole host of other
countries the Venezuelans the Cubans I
mean the eritreans we can go on and on
and on about countries that oh as policy
we we can't talk to them why not why
can't we talk to them I I I made the
arbitrary decision to go to Cuba last
year for the very first time the Cuban
uh the Cuban government had translated
my first two books into Spanish and
included them in the permanent
collection of the Cuban national library
this was a good opportunity I
went first of all they treated me like a
king
secondly to a man they expressed
admiration for the United States
they don't like our government so much
but it was more that people were puzzled
as to why our government hates them so
much everybody wants to work with us the
only person who expressed real
frustration I had a meeting with with
one of the vice presidents there are
three vice presidents of Cuba so we had
a meeting with
one and you know a couple of people in
my group
um a couple of people in my group group
said well you know now that Biden's in
uh maybe he'll open things up again so
this was supposed to be the crown jewel
in the Obama foreign policy and the
Cuban vice president said no all your
presidents are the same they blame us
for everything he goes we we can't even
keep the lights on every day our
children don't have shoes we don't have
medical supplies and medical equipment
and we're somehow a threat to the United
States you have relations with countries
that you have far far bigger problems
with than with us half of our population
lives in
Miami and he was right you know you
you've you've caused me to want to ask
you one more question because this this
notion which is so vitally important
about dialogue between governments um
you
know peace uh requires us to see the
world through the eyes of our enemies uh
otherwise we if we never have any kind
of strategic empathy at the end of the
day we're probably doomed so in that
vein I went to uh Russia for the first
time in um in my life in uh May of last
year and uh part of my trip was to Crea
and I went there in order to uh try to
establish a dialogue with Russians
because everybody in our country seemed
to be you know hostile to the idea of
speaking to Russians and uh I called up
the Russian Ambassador in Canada
beforehand heard that he for Mutual
acquaintance that he was familiar with
my critique of Canadian foreign policy I
asked him to set me up great people I
went there while I'm there while I was
in Crea I was in Moscow I went to Crea I
get a call from this guy named Adam Zebo
who's a columnist at a national
newspaper in Canada and he's stationed
in Ukraine at the time on the part
that's controlled by Kiev and he's
writing these intensely uh hostile
articles about Russia and so forth and
very Pro NATO and he wants to interview
me um that was in 2023 in the middle of
2023 he just came out in August of this
year John he said that at the time he
interviewed me uh and from the late 2022
he was working for the Canadian Security
intelligence services and the Ukrainian
intelligence Services of course he was
of course he didn't tell me this and if
he had I wouldn't have done the
interview uh and he never disclosed this
in any of his pieces about the Ukraine
war so the question I have for you
because you come from the intelligence
Community it occur one thing I should
add is that the newspaper that he works
for hasn't denied what he
said he himself has clarified that he
told his boss as the editors he was
doing this work for these two
intelligence agencies and the Canadian
government hasn't denied it there hasn't
been a peep so I recall that there was a
big investigative report then I think it
might have been by Bob Woodward uh way
back in the 80s or something where he
talked about plants from the
intelligence community and the media so
now that I have you here and you used to
work for the CIA I'm C ious what what
are your thoughts about this today in
the world in operate do you think that
this is the Zeos of this world the Adam
Zeos of this world are fairly they're
more numerous than we might want to want
to believe in terms of yeah yeah and and
you know what it's even worse than most
people think because the CIA I I can
only speak uh to the CIA but the CIA no
longer needs to recruit uh journalists
right they've co-opted all the
journalists uh I have a friend who's a
journalist for
Bloomberg uh Jason Leupold Jason's an
awesome investigative reporter he he's a
master of the Freedom of Information Act
to the point where a pentagon spokesman
once called him a Foya terrorist because
he was able to uncover so much
information he's the one who who broke
the Hillary Clinton um email server
story and he did that through the
Freedom of Information Act so he told me
once that he was just kind of board one
night he was in between
stories didn't really have anything
pending so he just kind of dashed off a
quick Freedom of Information Act request
to the CIA to the office of public
affairs asking for all emails between
the office of public affairs and
American journalists from one date to
another date he said he didn't have
anything in mind just was kind of
curious to see what was in there they
answered the
and what he found was for example Ken
delanian who was the chief National
Security correspondent for NBC News and
MSNBC here in the United States formerly
the the chief intelligence correspondent
for the Los Angeles
Times writes his articles and sends them
to the CIA for clearance before sending
them to his own editor oh my God can you
imagine this is a guy making you know a
million bucks a year he's supposed to be
the goto intelligence guy and he's
essentially just saying to the CIA well
what do you want me to say what do you
want me not to say here's what I'm
proposing what do you think about it
another thing that he
found was a journalist who wrote
something critical of the
CIA who sent it into the office of
public affairs for a comment saying hey
this is what I'm going to say I'm going
to criticize you do you have a comment
and they said so help us if you publish
this you are not invited to the
Christmas party and we will never give
you a quote again this was in the email
oh God in the email and he and he
dropped the
article you know the the
access yeah yeah so uh basically we
should assume that um um that this
problem is more widespread than one
columnist at the National Post I think
that's fair to say yes in any case it's
it's everywhere thank you so much for
speaking with me today John uh I hope we
can continue the conversation in the
future I'm sure we're GNA hear about
more about foreign interference I look
forward to talk to you about you know
other foreign policy issues of great
importance to us the the pleasure is
mine I look forward to staying in touch
okay and this is Demitri signing off
from kalamat Greece on September 28 2024